His face, his hair - look at it!
他的脸，他的头发，你看!
He's breathing...
他还在呼吸...
...and the TARDIS seems to be normal.
...而且TARDIS看起来很正常
Ben, what are we going to do? We can't just leave the Doctor there.
Ben, 我们该怎么办? 我们不能把博士扔那儿不管.
What, him? The Doctor?
什么, 他是博士?
Well, that's who came through the doors - there was no one else outside. Ben, do you remember what he said in the tracking room? Something about "This old body of mine is wearing a bit thin. "
嗯，从门外走进来的人就是他 - 外面也没有其他人
So he gets himself a new one?
这么说他有了个新的?
Well, yes.
嗯，是的.
Oh, do me a favour!
哦，得了吧!
Ben, whatever happened, happened in here.
Ben, 这里肯定发生了点什么.
But it's impossible!
但这不可能啊!
Not so long ago we'd have been saying that about a lot of things.
不久以前，我们还对好多事情说了这句话.
Oh, Ben!
哦, Ben!
Slower... Slower!
慢点... 慢点!
Concentrate on one thing... one thing!
聚焦在一个东西上... 就一个!
It's over.
过去了
Doctor?
博士?
The muscles are still a bit tight.
肌肉还有点紧.
What are we going to do?
我们该做点什么?
It is the Doctor. I know it is... I think.
他是博士. 我就知道... 我觉得.
It's not only his face that's changed - he doesn't even act like him.
不仅仅是他的脸变了 - 他的行为也不像.
Come on, it's time we sorted this out.
来吧，我们把这事搞清楚.
Now look here!
现在看这儿!
Hold that.
停住.
And tilt it.
斜点儿
Have you done with this?
你干过这个吗?
Put it down, put it down.
放下，放下.
Now, what's the game?
现在，玩什么游戏?
Ah!
啊!
The crusades, from Saladin.
十字军，撒拉丁
The Doctor was a great collector, wasn't he!
博士是个收藏家啊!
But you're the Doctor!
但你就是博士啊!
Oh, I don't look like him.
哦，我看着不像他.
Who are we?
我们是谁?
Don't you know?
你不知道吗?
Extermination!
Extermination! (Daleks 常用口号，意为"毁灭／终结"） （博士手里是一块来自Daleks的金属板）
Ah!
啊!
Ah, very good. Nails need growing.
啊，很好，指甲得长长.
Now look, the Doctor always wore this. So if you're him, it should fit now, shouldn't it?
看，博士总戴着这个，如果你是他，这个应该大小合适，对不对?
There - that settles it.
看 - 掉下来了.
I'd like to see a butterfly fit into a chrysalis case after it's spread its wings.
我想看看蝴蝶展开翅膀后怎么适应它的蛹
Then you did change!
你真的变了!
Life depends on change... and renewal.
生命依赖于变化... 和新生.
Oh, so that's it - you've been renewed, have ya?
哦，那就是了 - 你已经重生了，是吧?
I've been renewed, have I? That's it, I've been renewed!
我已经重生了，是吗？应该是了，我重生了!
It's part of the TARDIS - without it, I couldn't survive.
这是 TARDIS 的能力，没有它，我就不可能幸存.
Come here!
过来!
Come here.
到这里来.
The Doctor kept a diary, didn't he?
博士持有一本日记，对吧?
Yes.
是的.
I thought so. Now, I wonder where?
我记得是，不过现在在哪儿呢?
I wonder where?
在哪儿呢?
He's a very different Doctor, Ben.
嗯, 很可能. 不过我们现在到底什么情况?
Hello?
哈罗?
Hello? Is there anyone there? Hello?
哈罗? 有人吗? 哈罗?
Hello? Why don't they come?
哈罗? 他们怎么还不来?
Ah, so you've come at last. I'm from Earth. I'm the Examin...
啊, 你终于来了. 我从地球来的. 我是监察员...
"Earth Examiner. Accord every access. Vulcan. "
"地球监察员. 授予所有权限. Vulcan. "
Doctor?! Where are you?
博士?! 你在哪儿?
Whoa, they're hot!
喔, 好热!
Hmm, do you think the air's like this everywhere?
唔, 是不是到处的空气都像这样?
Nah - might be just round here. Don't want too many lung full of it, I know that. Here, when I was a kid, we used to live opposite a brewery. You could take a walk and get tipsy all in one go!
不 - 可能只是这一片才这样. 别使劲吸气, 我知道的.
It's beautiful!
好美啊!
No, don't touch it, Polly!
别，别碰, Polly!
I wasn't going to.
我没打算碰.
No, it's quicksilver - it gets through the pores.
这是水银 - 会从这些气泡里面出来.
Where is the Doctor, or whatever he is, got to?
博士要去哪儿啊？ - 就算他是博士吧
What's the matter? Hey, Polly!
什么情况? 嘿, Polly!
Hey, Doctor - wherever you are! Quick, there's something happened to Polly!
嘿，博士 - 你在哪儿! 快点, Polly这里出事了!
Quick, over this way!
快点，这边!
Doctor!
博士!
Ah, Quinn, there you are. What have you got there?
啊, Quinn, 你在这里啊. 你在这里发现了什么?
My people have found two more of them by one of the pools.
我的人在其中一个池子边还发现了两个.
This one's got a nasty bruise on the back of his head. Fallen over his feet and knocked himself out, I suppose.
这个人脑后受了严重的伤. 然后晕倒了, 我推断是这样。
I suppose so.
我也觉得.
Why don't they use the kit we send them?
他们怎么不用我们送给他们的器材呢？
Yes, the other two have had a rather bad dose of fumes - the girl has anyway.
是的，另两个人也吸入了烟气 - 至少那个女孩儿是.
Girl?
女孩?
Yes, but she'll recover.
是, 但她会恢复的.
These comic-opera guards of yours do have some uses after all.
你这些着装搞笑的保安总算还有点作用.
I pick them for their physical fitness.
他们是按身体素质挑选出来的.
I thought it wasn't for their I.Q. Give me a hand with the Examiner, will you.
我也觉得不是按他们的智商. 帮一下监察员，行吗.
I wonder why Earth has chosen to send an Examiner to Vulcan? Just now, I mean?
我很好奇地球为什么要送一个监察员到 Vulcan 来? 我是说，为什么现在?
I don't know.
我不知道.
A mystery, isn't it? He isn't due for another two years.
一个谜题啊. 他应该两年后才上任的.
How do you feel?
你感觉如何?
Oh...
哦...
We saw your rocket overshoot the landing area.
我们看到你们的火箭飞出着陆区了.
Eh?
哦?
Don't worry - most of the ships from Earth do over-shoot. I'm Quinn, Deputy Governor.
别担心 - 大多数地球来的飞船都会飞出去. 我是 Quinn, 这里的副总督.
Bragen, Head of Security.
Bragen, 安保队长.
Let's get all back shall we? I'll take the girl.
我们回去吧? 我负责带这个女孩儿.
Lesterson?
Lesterson?
Look at this.
看这里.
They've just brought in an Examiner from Earth, and a couple of assistants.
他们刚带进来了一位地球来的监察员，还有几位助手．
An Examiner? What's he here for?
监察员? 来干什么?
I thought you'd know.
我以为你知道.
Ah, it's the capsule, it must be.
啊，冲着太空舱来的，一定是.
Well, they can't stop me working on it, I can tell you that.
他们不可能拦着我继续搞这个，我跟你说.
Could anyone?
有人能嘛?
The Governor's always been difficult about it. But surely they wouldn't send someone all the way from Earth just to...?
总督那里就一直不难搞. 但他们当然不会从地球送个人过来，只为了...?
Look, what about the meeting?
那，会面怎么办?
Meeting?
会面?
Yes - I've arranged everything. Can we still use the old rocket room?
是的 - 我都已经安排好了. 我们可以继续使用旧的火箭室吗?
Yes, I suppose so. But I do wish you wouldn't get mixed up with these pressure groups, Janley.
是的，我觉得可以. 但我觉得你不要把这些压力集团搞混了, Janley.
Well, somebody has to do something. The colony's running down and you know it.
这样，总有人得做点什么. 这块基地在走下坡路了，你知道的.
Well, I am too busy.
啊，我太忙了.
But if we ran things, you'd have better facilities, more money. I wish you'd take an interest.
但如果我们有所动作的话，你就能有更好的设备，更多的钱．我期望你上点心.
Now look, I don't mind letting you have the use of one of my rooms now and again, Janley, but don't try to involve me.
看, 我并不介意你常常来借用我的房间, Janley, 但别把我扯进去.
This is what I find important. Two hundred years in a mercury swamp...
这才是我觉得重要地位东西. 在水银沼泽里待了两百年...
...and this piece of metal that dropped from it. Look - a couple of minutes polishing and it's as good as new.
...这片金属是从上面掉下来的. 看 - 花几分钟抛光一下就跟新的一样了.
Wonderful.
漂亮.
Rain, damp, heat, mercury - nothing touches this metal. No corrosion, Janley - think of that.
雨水, 湿气, 热浪, 水银 - 什么也不能侵袭这块金属. 没有锈斑, Janley - 想想吧.
Well, I hope the Examiner lets you go on with your experiments.
只是, 我期望监察员能允许你继续你的实验.
Frankly, I doubt it.
坦白的说, 我有点怀疑.
I think the Governor's brought the Examiner here to stop you opening the capsule.
我觉得总督让监察员过来就是为了阻止你打开太空舱的.
You should join our group, Lesterson. You might need us one day.
你该加入我们组的, Lesterson. 某天你会需要我们.
So the murdered man was the real Examiner?
所以被谋杀的人就是真的监察员?
Well, didn't you see who did it?
那么，你有没有看到是谁干的?
The Doctor got this button though.
博士, 这里多了颗纽扣.
Well, I think it's pretty dull around here. I don't know why we don't just go back to the TARDIS.
我觉得这挺无聊的. 我不明白我们为什么不回到 TARDIS 去.
Doctor, are you going to let them think you're the real Examiner?
博士，你是想让他们觉得你就是真正的监察员吗?
Well, won't that be dangerous?
嗯，那会不会比较危险?
Look, why don't you stop blowing that thing and talk to us properly?
看，你能不能不再吹那个，认真跟我们说说?
Ben!
Ben!
Now don't you start - it's bad enough with him!
你现在别说话 - 跟他在一起就够糟的了!
Well, he hasn't done anything.
他什么也没做.
No, that's just the trouble! He knows what happened back at the TARDIS, yet will he tell us? Will he come out and say? Will he admit to being the Doctor?
不，那就是麻烦所在! 他知道那会儿 TARDIS 里发生了什么
Come in!
请进!
I am Hensell - the Governor. I trust you're all feeling much better?
我是 Hensell - 这里的总督. 我想想你们感觉好点了吧?
Huh, I've felt worse, Governor.
唔，我感觉更差了，总督.
The Governor?
总督?
If Earth had seen fit to warn us you were coming, we might, possibly, have been able to guide you down to the landing area.
如果地球早点告诉我们你要来，我们就可能可以帮助你着陆了.
If Earth didn't warn you we were coming, Governor, they must have had a very good reason. I wonder what it was?
如果地球没告诉你，总督，他们一定有一个很好理由. 我很好奇到底是什么?
Now look here - I run this Colony. I'm entitled to know why you've come to Vulcan. What is your brief?
你看 - 我负责这块基地. 我有权知道你为什么到 Vulcan 来. 简单说说?
I am the Examiner.
我是监察员.
Why are you here?
为什么来这儿?
To examine. And I intend to start my examination at once!
监察. 我现在就要开始检查!
Someone's leaked reports about these rebel groups - that's it, isn't it?
有人密报说这里有人叛乱，是为了这个吧，是吗?
Your turn now, Governor.
该你了，总督.
There is Lesterson's capsule.
应该是 Lesterson 的那个舱体.
Internal affairs are my business, Bragen. Please don't interfere!
内部事物归我管， Bragen. 请不要来干扰我们!
Please go on.
请继续.
The capsule. It was found in a mercury swamp. It must have been here for centuries.
这个舱体，是在一个水银沼泽里发现的. 可能在那里已经几个世纪了.
Interesting - continue.
有意思 - 继续.
For centuries before the Earth colony arrived. I felt it might be dangerous, it might contain bacteria.
在地球殖民者到达前的几个世纪. 我觉得它可能很危险, 它可能带有细菌.
I shall examine the capsule... later. You may leave us.
我应该检查一下这个舱体... 待会儿吧. 你们可以走了
I shall look forward to your report. Bragen, see that the Examiner and his party... get some proper clothes, will you?
我期待你的报告. Bragen, 确保监察员和他的随从 ... 换身得体的衣服，好吧?
We are wearing proper clothes!
我们穿得很得体!
Oh, how did he get that thing back again? That was a bit of a cheek, wasn't it? Er, seeing if the Governor was the guy that you got the button off?
哦，他怎么拿回那个东西的? 有点厚颜无耻吧? 呃，看看总督能不能把他个徽章拿下来?
Doctor?
博士?
Mmm?
唔?
When he was talking to you, you were staring at the other man?
他跟你说话的时候，你盯着其他人看?
Yes, very rude of me, wasn't it? Terrible manners.
是的，我太失礼了，是吧? 可怕的修养.
To tell you the truth, I was studying his reactions - seeing if he agreed with the story.
跟你说实话吧，我是在研究他的反应 - 看他是否赞同那个故事.
Did he?
他赞同吗?
Must have a look at that capsule.
得看一眼那个舱体.
You know, you wanna watch you don't take this Examiner stuff a bit too far.
你最好注意一下, 扮演监察员不要过于投入了.
Our answers must come from that mercury swamp.
我们的答案只能从那个水银沼泽里面寻找.
'Cos at least one bloke ain't gonna be fooled.
因为至少有一个家伙不会被骗.
When Bragen found us, he definitely said space capsule.
Bragen 找到我们的时候，他绝对说的是“太空”舱.
Look, you're not going to fool the guy that did the real Examiner in!
你骗不了那个把真监察员召来的人!
Bragen! What's all this nonsense about having to have a pass to see the Examiner?
Bragen! 为什么见一下监察员还得先征得同意?
It's the Governor's idea.
这是总督的主意.
Surely it doesn't apply to me?
当然这对我不适用吧?
It's not my order, Quinn. I expect the Governor wants to keep people away from him.
不是我下的命令, Quinn. 我觉得总督不想让人靠近他.
It sounded like one of your red-tape ideas.
听起来像是你们这类 red-tape 的主意.
It has nothing to do with me.
这跟我没关系.
Right!
正确!
Oh!
哦!
Sorry, Janley.
对不起, Janley.
My fault.
我的错.
Are you all right?
你没事吧?
Yes. Lesterson's just cleared me out of his lab.
是的. Lesterson 刚把我从实验室赶出来了.
Is the Examiner going to let him open the capsule?
监察员会允许他打开舱体吗?
I don't know. I'm on my way there now... if I can push past Bragen's army of layabouts.
我不知道. 我正在往那边走... 如果我能挤过 Bragen 的保安人墙的话.
Where did you get this?
你在哪里得到这个的?
It dropped from the capsule.
从舱体上掉下来的.
Dropped?
掉下来?
Yes, when it was being hauled into the laboratory. But, you can see! This metal could revolutionise space travel. That's why I'm insisting that we open it. Well, who knows what other marvels there may be inside?
是的, 把它拖进实验室的时候. 不过，你看! 这种金属可以会对我们的太空旅行技术产生革命性影响.
But Lesterson, I didn't think you could open it?
不过 Lesterson, 我没想到你能打开它?
Well, I have a theory. I'm convinced that the opening mechanism on the other side is either here, or here.
我有一个理论. 我推断打开的方法是在两端，要么这边，要么这边.
Extermination...
Extermination (终结）...
Now, my theory is that I can insert a laser ray in this ridge here.
我的理论是可以在这个背脊处注入激光束.
The ray spreads, fuses the opening device and gets us in.
光束散开, 触发开门设备，我们就可以进去了.
Examiner, I shall have to make it your responsibility.
监察员, 我觉得该你来决策了.
A laser? Why not? It shouldn't be too difficult.
激光? 没问题? 不会太难.
Well, we'll try the other side.
我们来试试另外一边.
Hmm, it's a bit... disappointing.
唔, 有一点... 让人失望.
Not really. This is just an entry bay, isn't it?
不会. 这只是门廊, 对吧?
Yes, I... I suppose so.
是的... 我觉得是.
Well, this doesn't get us very far does it?
那并没有让我们走多远是吧?
Ah, getting into the rest of the capsule will take time, Governor.
进到舱体其它部分就需要时间了，总督.
Well, can't you use that torch thing again? That must be an opening door.
你不能再用一下那个光束吗？那肯定是一个门.
Well, I should have to measure it up and find out where the lock mechanism is.
我得考察一下，看看锁机关在哪儿.
And I think we'll leave if for tonight.
我觉得今晚就到此为止吧.
Leave it?
到此为止?
Leave it for tonight? But what did we come here for?
就这样了? 那我们来这儿干什么?
That is my decision, Governor.
这是我的决定，总督.
But, good heavens above, man!
但是，苍天在上!
Two hundred years, you say, this has been buried?
两百年，你说它被埋了?
Oh, at least. Now, there must be something in the inner compartment.
哦，至少有. 里面的隔间里一定有什么东西.
We shall be able to find out where it came from originally.
我们应该可以搞明白它是从哪里来的.
It didn't come from this planet - Vulcan.
它并不是来自这个星球 - Vulcan.
Oh no, no, no. The metal is quite alien.
哦，不不不. 这个金属很外星.
Alien, yes. Very alien. Goodnight.
外星，是的. 非常外星. 晚安.
What's he up to now?
他这是怎么了?
Ben, we're not going to let him out of our sight.
Ben, 不要让他离开我们的视线.
Well, Lesterson, you got your way. Was it worth sending for this Examiner? This idiotic Examiner?
好了，Lesterson, 你有路子. 不过你找来这监察员值得吗? 就这个愚蠢的家伙?
I didn't send for him. I thought you did.
不是我找你的. 我还以为是你呢.
Why don't you let me talk to the Examiner, Hensell? I can find out what's he's here for.
你为什么不让我跟监察员说话，Hensell? 我能找出他来这里的原因.
No, no, no, no, you keep away from him. We'll leave him to work with Lesterson here. We've all got enough to do without having to worry about some amateur critic from Earth interfering.
不不不, 你离他远点. 我们让他跟 Lesterson 呆一起吧.
But with five minutes, I _...
但只要５分钟, 我 _...
You heard what I said, Quinn. You won't mind keeping the Examiner busy, Lesterson? I don't mind what you do with him so long as you keep his nose... out of our business.
你听到我的话了, Quinn. 你不介意让监察员忙得团团转吧, Lesterson?
Yes. All right.
好. 没问题.
All right. Well, we shall talk about it tomorrow.
就这样. 我们明早再讨论.
Ben!
Ben!
What?
什么?
Shh! He's in the corridor.
嘘! 他在走廊里.
Who is?
谁?
The Doctor, you clod! Come on - quick!
博士, 你个笨蛋! 过来 - 快!
He's going towards Lesterson's lab.
他往 Lesterson 的实验室去了.
Of course - to the space capsule!
当然 - 那个太空舱!
Come on.
快点.
Polly, Ben, come in and meet the Daleks.
Polly, Ben, 进来见见 Daleks.
What?
什么?
The Daleks.
Daleks.
You could have opened this before.
你以前就打开过这个.
These two pieces of metal are identical. The Doctor got one of them from the Daleks himself.
这两片金属是一样的. 其中一片是博士直接从 Daleks 那里得到的.
Why do you keep saying the Doctor if you mean you?
为什么你一直说“博士怎样怎样”，但你意思是在说你自己?
I knew I should find them here - I knew it.
我知道我可以在这里找到他们 - 我就知道.
Ah, they look harmless, not very lively.
啊, 他们看起来是无害的, 并不活跃.
What do you think? Two hundred years in a swamp and you wouldn't look very lively either. Nothing could live through that, could it?
你想什么呢? 在沼泽里呆200年，你也看起来不活跃. 没有什么东西能熬过来，是吧?
Live?
活的?
Nothing human, no.
不是人类, 不.
Doctor, look!
博士, 看!
What's the matter?
怎么回事?
Well, there were three Daleks in here! What's happened to the other one?
这里本来有三个 Daleks 的! 另外一个发生了什么?
Doctor!
博士!